Guide to the William H. Wright Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
William H. Wright papers
1897-1954
WA MSS S-2564
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
0.42
(1 box)
The papers consist of correspondence, printed materials, personal papers, and photographs of William H. Wright of Chicago, Illinois, documenting the mining industry in Washington State's St. Helens Mining District during the first decades of the twentieth century. The bulk of the material is correspondence relating to investments that William and his wife Ella made in southwestern Washington, and includes materials documenting stockholder relations with specific Washington and Oregon mining corporations. The papers span the years 1897 to 1954, and include letters addressed to Wright's wife, in-laws, and son.
Wright, William H., 1854-1937
Eaton, James, 1831-1921
Meiser, J. A. (Jesse A.)
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from Charles Apfelbaum on the Winlock William Miller, Jr. Memorial Fund, 2006.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
WILLIAM H. WRIGHT (1857-1939)
William H. Wright was born in 1854. He lived in Chicago, Illinois with his wife, Ella R. Wright. The Wrights invested in the St. Helens Mining District in Washington state at the urging of Ella's brother, E. A. Sessions. Sessions was officially involved with multiple mining corporations in the St. Helens area during the first two decades of the twentieth century, including the Cascadia Mining and Development Company, the Levens Ledge Gold Mining Company, and the Polar Star Mining Company.
The Wrights had a son, Henry E. Wright. William H. Wright died on August 16, 1937.
Scope and Contents
The William H. Wright Papers consist of correspondence, printed materials, personal papers, and photographs that document the mining industry in the St. Helens Mining District of southwestern Washington. The papers also document stockholder relations with specific Washington and Oregon mining corporations. The bulk of the material relates to financial investments that William H. Wright and his wife, Ella, made in the Cascadia Mining and Development Company, the Levens Ledge Gold Mining Company, and the Polar Star Mining Company. The papers span the years 1897-1954, and include letters addressed to Wright's wife, in-laws, and son.
Series I. Correspondence is organized into three subseries: Family Correspondence, Business Correspondence and Third Party Correspondence. Family Correspondence consists primarily of letters from William Wright's brother-in-law, Eugene A. Sessions. According to a letter he wrote in 1898, Sessions was a proprietor of a grocery and supply store in Portland, Oregon. His letters to his sister and her husband, mostly addressed to the latter, describe mining investment opportunities in the mining district around St. Helens, and trace Session's career as a mining investor and entrepreneur and the increasing financial involvement of the Wrights in his ventures. Sessions' letters also discuss the growth and financial state of his mining and other business enterprises, which included the Cascadia Mining and Development Co., the Levens Ledge Gold Mining Co., and the Polar Star Mining Co. Letters from Sessions to his parents in Woodstock, Illinois are also present.
Business Correspondence consists primarily of stockholder letters to the Wrights from the Cascadia Mining and Development Company and the Polar Star Mining Company as well as letters replying to William Wright's inquiries about these corporations in the 1930s. Third Party Correspondence includes letters reporting on E. A. Sessions's mining properties in the St. Helens Mining District as well as two letters written by Henry E. Wright concerning his father's financial interests in corporations in the area.
Series II. Printed Materials consists of prospectuses and brochures for the Cascadia Mining and Development Company and the Levens Ledge Gold Mining Company of Portland, Oregon.
Series III. Personal Papers is organized into Financial and Legal Papers and Other Papers. Other Papers includes newspaper clippings, a map of the St. Helens Mining District, and a phone book containing birth and death dates for members of the Sessions and Wright families.
Series IV. Photographs consists of three photographs by James H. Eaton: "Soda Springs Camp", a captioned image picturing pack animals, men, and one woman in June 1897; "Minnie Lee", an image of the entrance of the Minnie Lee mine; and "Polar Star", an image of four unidentified miners in front of the entrance of the Polar Star mine. An uncaptioned mounted photograph by J. A. Meiser of two loggers sitting in the cleft of a tree they've nearly sawn through is also present.
Copper mines and mining -- Washington (State) -- St. Helens Mining District; Gold mines and mining -- Oregon -- Douglas County; Gold mines and mining -- Washington (State) -- St. Helens Mining District; Loggers -- Washington (State); Miners -- Washington (State); Mines and mineral resources -- Washington (State) -- St. Helens Mining District; Silver mines and mining -- Washington (State) -- St. Helens Mining District; Stockholders -- United States; Saint Helens Mining District (Wash.); Saint Helens Mining District (Wash.) -- Maps; Maps (documents) -- Washington (State) -- Saint Helens Mining District; Photographic prints -- Washington (State) -- Saint Helens Mining District; Prospectuses -- Washington (State) -- Saint Helens Mining District -- 20th Century; Miners -- Washington (State); Stockholders -- United States; Sessions, E. A. (Eugene A.); Wright, Ella R., 1857-1939; Wright, Henry E.; Wright, William H., 1854-1937; Cascadia Mining and Development Company; Levens Ledge Gold Mining Company; Polar Star Mining Company
- Correspondence, 1898-1930; Series I; 0.21; (0.5 boxes)
  Scope and Contents
  Series I. Correspondence, is organized into three subseries: Family Correspondence, Business Correspondence, and Third Party Correspondence. Each subseries is arranged chronologically.
  - FAMILY CORRESPONDENCE
    - Correspondence, 1898-1930 (Box 1, Folder 1-6)
  - BUSINESS CORRESPONDENCE
    - Cascadia Mining and Development Company, 1908-27, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Cowlitz, Chehalis, and Cascade Railway, 1927 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Levens Ledge Gold Mining Company, 1904 Jan 15 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Oregon. Corporation Dept., 1930, 1931 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Oregon. Office of the Secretary of State, 1920 Apr 10 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Polar Star Mining Company, 1929-31 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Thompson, Wm., 1908 Oct 14 (Box 1, Folder 13)
      Regarding Dallas, Tex. property purchased by E. A. Sessions in 1883
    - Washington (State). Office of the Secretary of State, 1930 Apr 3 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - THIRD PARTY CORRESPONDENCE
    - Fassett, Charles M., Analytical and Consulting Chemist and Meallurgist, to T. T. Burkhart, Spokane, Wash., 1904 Apr 9 (Box 1, Folder 15)
      Report on Sessions's group of mining properties in St. Helens Mining District, Washington
    - Hanley, Robert E. to E. A. Sessions, 1904 Dec 5 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Wright, H. E. to Polar Star Mining Company, 1954 Mar 16 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Washington (State). Office of the Secretary of State to H. E. Wright, 1954 Apr 7 (Box 1, Folder 18)
      Regarding dissolution of Cascadia Mining & Development Co.
    - Watson, W. H. to J. T. Henwood, Levens Ledge Mining Company, Riddles, Ore., n.d. (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Empty envelopes, 1969, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Printed Materials, n.d; Series II; 0.07; (0.2 boxes)
  Arrangement
  Series II. Printed Materials, is arranged alphabetically.
  - The Cascadia Mining and Development Company, brochure (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Cascadia Mining and Development Co.: Copper, Gold, Silver, prospectus (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - The Cascadia Mining and Development Company, prospectus (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - The Cascadia Mining and Development Company, prospectus (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - A Gold Mine, prospectus for Levens Ledge Gold Mining Company, Portland, Oregon (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Sessions, E. A. Mining No Gamble, Levens Ledge property circular, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 26)
- Personal Papers, 1906-1954; Series III; 0.07; (0.1 boxes)
  Series III. Personal Papers is organized into two subseries: Financial and Legal Papers and Other Papers. Each subseries is arranged chronologically.
  - FINANCIAL AND LEGAL PAPERS
    - Contract, blank, between Cascadia Mining and Development Company and O.J. Gray of Portland, Ore., 1917 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - Opinion of title for property of Ella R. Wright, County McHenry, Ill., 1919 May 19 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - Bill of sale for Alton Watch and Mdse. Co., Cook County, Ill. William H. Wright to Harry E. Wright, 1922 Dec 14 (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - Tax receipt, 1953, for H. E. Wright (St. Anthony Mining Co.), Iowa County, Wisc., 1954 Mar 29 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - OTHER PAPERS
    - Newspaper clippings, 1906-54, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - Diagram, pencil, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - Map of St. Helens Mining District, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 33)
    - Phone book, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 34)
      Includes birth and death dates for Millar, Sessions and Wright families
- Photographs, 1897-1901; Series IV; 0.07; (0.2 boxes)
  Series IV. Photographs is arranged chronologically.
  - "Soda Springs Camp", 1897 Jun (Box 1, Folder 35)
    Annotated: "Taking in party to develop the property in June 1897"
  - [Two loggers in tree cut with crosscut saw], 1901 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - "Minnie Lee", n.d. (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - "Polar Star", n.d. (Box 1, Folder 38)